rwe.com 2019-04-06

# Privacy Policy

### RWE on Data Protection

We would like to thank you for your interest in our company. We respect your privacy and are committed to protecting it through our privacy practices as described in this Policy. For this purpose, we have taken technical and organizational measures to ensure that the relevant laws are observed. Below you will find out what information we collect and how we handle it.

For the here presented website content is responsible:

**RWE Aktiengesellschaft  
**Altenessener Straße 35  
45141 Essen  
T +49(0)201-51790  
F +49(0)201-51795005

### Personal data

You decide whether or not you want to disclose your personal data to us, for example in the context of a registration, contact request or similar. We generally use your personal information to respond to your query, process your order, or provide you with access to specific information or offers.    

### General information

As you visit our website or retrieve a file, information about this process is stored in a log file on our Web server. This information is not personally identifiable. We are therefore unable to trace which user accessed which data. This means that when a user accesses our website, data is automatically collected and stored that your browser transmits to us.

This includes:

  * the domain name of the website from the which you came
  * the pages you have visited on our website
  * names of the files retrieved
  * date and time of a retrieval
  * name of the Internet Service Provider
  * as well as operating system and browser version of your PC (if applicable)
  * Hostname of the accessing computer (IP address)
  * language settings 

This data is collected for security and statistical purposes and to optimise the quality of our website. These data are not allocated to specific persons and are not merged with other data sources. The data is stored for 6 months and then deleted. Your data is not disclosed to third parties. Merely through order of responsible national authorities we can be obligated in individual cases to publish personal data, if this should be necessary for averting danger, criminal prosecution or for other legally regulated reasons.

### IP addresses

In order to allow you an anonymous use of our websites, we deliberately refrain from logging IP addresses. Your IP address will be pseudonymised by us before it is stored in our web server log file in a data protection-compliant procedure. The pseudonymised IP addresses are used by us, for example, to recognise and counteract attacks or to compile web statistics.

### Web analysis and web optimization through cookies and tracking pixels

We use cookies and tracking technologies on our websites. These serve the purpose of optimising our websites, improving services and marketing our products. The technologies used and their functions are as follows. 

When you visit one of our websites, we place information on your computer in the form of cookies, which we automatically recognise the next time you visit our site. Cookies are text files that are stored in the Internet browser on the user’s computer system. Whenever a user accesses a website, a cookie can be stored on the operating system of the user. That cookie contains a definitive series of characters which enables unique identification of that browser the next time it accesses the website.

The use of cookies helps us to offer you unrestricted use of our website. They allow us to make your visit to our site as convenient as possible. For instance, cookies enable us to adapt a website to your personal interests or store your user name to prevent you having to re-enter it every time you visit.

We also apply tracking pixels on our websites. Tracking pixels are small graphics on websites that enable log-in data to be recorded and analysed. When a user visits the website, these tracking pixels write information on the cookie file within the user’s browser. By using pixels, we are able to offer you targeted information and content.

On our websites, you have the option of viewing and editing our cookie and pixel settings here. However, please be aware that some technically essential cookies and pixels have to be used in order to maintain the functionality of our websites.

You will find an overview of the cookies and pixels used on our websites, the data processed in each case and the relevant recipients right here. 

RWE uses cookies and pixels of the following categories:

  * ### Essential cookies and pixels

Essential cookies serve to maintain the technically sound operation of our website. They ensure the stability of the website, support secure log-in, and save the current progress of your order, your log-in details and your shopping cart. You can see which essential cookies we use from our full List of Cookies and Pixels, available here.

The data collected about you in this way is anonymised by technical measures to ensure it can no longer be traced back to you. This data is not stored with other personal details we collect from you. When you access one of our websites, you will be informed via a banner message about our use of cookies and also referred to this Data Protection Information. In addition, reference will be made in this context to the method you can use to block the storage of cookies in your browser settings.

This processing of your aforementioned data is necessary to safeguard the legitimate interests of RWE and is justified by balancing the respective interests in favor of RWE. Without using this data, some functions of our internet presence cannot be offered. It is essential for this process that the browser is also recognisable after you have switched pages. RWE also has a legitimate interest in processing your aforementioned personal data; namely to communicate relevant information about our intentions and business activities by operating its own websites in accordance with their intended function. Your justifiable interest that the aforementioned data is not used for this purpose does not outweigh the legitimate interest of RWE, since RWE uses this data appropriately and in accordance with the stated purpose and you also have an interest in being able to access our website in a customer-friendly manner.

**You have the right to object at any time to processing of your data which has occurred as the result of a balancing of interests, if there are grounds for objection arising from your particular situation. Please refer to paragraph “Objection” in this context. The simplest way for you to lodge your objection is to use the relevant opt-out cookie/pixel via our List of Cookies and Pixelshere.**

  * ### Analytical cookies

We also use cookies that help us analyse the surfing habits of users. Analytical cookies allow us to analyse the websites so we can measure the performance of our pages and improve them accordingly. In this context, we use cookies for so-called reach measurement. With the aid of these cookies, we can compile statistical profiles which are not traceable to an individual person but only relate to statistical groups. These are then used to analyse visitor habits and click patterns as well as the demographic features of our website visitors. You can view the List of Cookies and Pixels we use here. This provides information about the analytical cookies we use and also gives you the option of using all of them or objecting to the use of specific cookies and pixels. The data collected from you in this way is anonymised by technical measures to ensure it can no longer be traced back to you. This data is not stored with other personal details we collect from you. When you access one of our websites, you will be informed via a banner message about our use of cookies and also referred to this Data Protection Information. In addition, reference will be made in this context to the method you can use to block the storage of cookies in your browser settings.

This processing of your data as described above is required to safeguard the legitimate interests of RWE and is justified by balancing the respective interests in favour of RWE. RWE also has a legitimate interest in processing the aforementioned personal data, namely to communicate relevant information about our intentions and business activities by operating its own websites in accordance with their intended function. Your justifiable interest that the aforementioned data is not used for this purpose does not outweigh the legitimate interest of RWE, since RWE uses this data appropriately and in accordance with the stated purpose and you have the option of blocking the storage of cookies.

**You have the right to object at any time to processing of your data which occurs as the result of a balancing of interests, if there are grounds for objecting from your particular situation. Please refer to paragraph “Objection” in this context. The simplest way to lodge your objection is to use the relevant opt-out cookie and pixel available via our List of Cookies and Pixelshere.**

  * ### Marketing Cookies

Marketing cookies help us offer you personalised advertising on rwe.com and beyond. You can see the marketing cookies we use from our full List of Cookies and Pixels, available here.

In this context, we also use cookies for purposes of remarketing, retargeting or lookalike retargeting. Retargeting is where a cookies with the relevant information enables recognition of the user’s browser so it can be retargeted on external websites. On the basis of the accumulated cookie information, statistical twins of the original cookie profiles can also be identified and addressed. This is commonly referred to as lookalike retargeting.

Furthermore, we also use a so-called dynamic tracking system. The system serves to determine the services of the various marketing channels of the innogy web shop. When you visit the web shop, data from your browser is collected for the purpose of statistical analysis. This data is forwarded to various technical and statistical service providers as part of an order management process. Collection of this data occurs via a pixel that is integrated within every web shop.

We also use cookies in this context for use-related advertising (so-called behavioral advertising). On our websites, data containing user information, (e.g. websites visited, number of visits, visiting times, time spent on individual pages), is stored by means of cookies and the hard drive of the user. Theser user profiles are anonymized and analysed by a technical (statistical) evaluation process in order to later offer a selection of suitable online offers on other websites (e.g. via banner advertising) that are likely to be of interest to the particular user. This behavioural targeting is carried out by third-party companies, whose names can be viewed in this list here. They also provide advertising for the websites of other companies. These third-party companies then compile user profiles themselves by means of cookies and apply their own targeting systems to use the collected data for the purpose of selecting suitable advertising for particular users..

When you access our websites, you will be informed via so-called cookie banners about our use of cookies for marketing purposes and your consent for processing of personal information used in this context will be sought. As part of that disclosure process, you will  also be referred to this Data Protection Information. The legal basis for processing personal data via the use of cookies and pixels for marketing purposes is your expressive consent.

**You have the right at any time to revoke your consent with future effect, without affecting the legality of any processing that occurred on the basis of the consent obtained from you prior to its revocation. The simplest way for you to revoke your consent is to use the relevant opt-out cookie/pixel via our cookie and pixel listhere.**

  * ### Social Media Cookies

Social media cookies give you the option of being linked direct to your social media account if required. This allows you to share websites in social networks and post comments these. You can see the cookies we use from our full list of cookies and pixels, which is available here and you also have the option of using all of them or objecting to the use of specific cookies and pixels.

We also use cookies for the purpose of social media tracking. Using cookies gives us the option of sharing data with social media companies (such as Google or Facebook) by way of a so-called hash value, in order to be able to offer you personalised content in the form of banners and advertisements. It is not possible for us or our service providers to draw conclusions about you as a person. Usage-based targeting occurs in three steps: data collection via so-called tracking pixels, storage and processing of the log file information and ultimate use of that information in the form of retargeting or lookalike targeting.

Social media pixels and cookies are only activated and only transmit data once you have given us your prior consent via the settings of the cookie law banner. When you access our websites, you will be informed via so-called cookie banners about our use of social media cookies for marketing purposes, and your consent for processing of personal information used in this context will be sought. As part of that disclosure process, you will also be referred to this Data Protection Information. The legal basis for processing personal data via the use of social media cookies and pixels for marketing purposes is your express consent.

**You have the right at any time to revoke your consent with future effect, without affecting the legality of any processing that occurred on the basis of the consent obtained from you prior to its revocation. The simplest way for you to revoke your consent is to use the relevant opt-out cookie/pixel via our List of Cookies and Pixelshere.**

  * ### Duration of Storage

After collecting the information transmitted to us via cookies and pixels, it is stored by us for the following periods of time, and then automatically deleted.

**Cookie-Category** | **Storage period**  
---|---  
Analytical Cookies | 24 Months  
Marketing Cookies | 3 Months  
Social Media Cookies | 3 Months  
Session Cookies | 24 Hours  
  
Session cookies are small units of information which we store in the working memory of your computer. A randomly generated, unique identification number forms part of a session cookie and is called the Session ID. Each cookie also contains the details of its origin and storage period.

### Children

Children should not submit personal information to RWE websites without the consent of the parent or guardian. RWE encourages all parents and guardians to instruct their children in the safe and responsible use of personal data on the Internet. In any event, RWE will not knowingly collect, use, or otherwise disclose personally identifiable information about children in any way.

### Security

RWE takes precautions to ensure the security of your personal information. Your data is conscientiously protected against loss, destruction, falsification, manipulation and unauthorized access or disclosure.

### Links to other websites

The RWE websites contain links to other websites. As the provider of our websites, we are solely responsible for the content of our own online presence. From these own contents, the contents created by other providers are to be differentiated, for which we take no responsibility and do not adopt their contents. We have no control over the fact that the linked website operators comply with the relevant data protection regulations. This Privacy Policy does not apply to websites of other providers, even if they are accessed via links on the website. Therefore, please observe the respective provisions of the other providers for data protection. Therefore, we cannot assume any liability for these external contents. If you find a relevant violation, we thank you for your reference. We will then remove the link if necessary after examination.

### Corporate appearances in social media (fan pages on Facebook, Twitter, Instagram etc.)

By representing of our company also via social media channels we intend to strengthen the ac-tive communication to you and offer you the possibility to inform yourself about our products and services.  
It should be noted that processing of personal data in countries outside the European Union cannot be excluded in the context of these company appearances. This may entail the risk of a more difficult enforcement of rights, which represents a risk for the individual user.

In case of the visit of the corresponding company appearances, cookies are usually stored on your computer. These cookies record usage behavior and user interests. As a basic rule, the data obtained from these cookies are used for market research and advertising purposes, whereby, due to the usage behaviour, advertising is shown that presumably corresponds to the interests of the user, i.e. you.   
Furthermore, you may be asked by the operator of the respective social medium for permission to process your data.

Via the so-called "Insights" of Facebook pages, statistical data of different categories can be accessed by us via our Facebook page. These statistics are generated and made available by Facebook. As the operator, we have no influence on the generation and display of these statistics. We cannot deactivate this function or prevent the generation and processing of data. For a selectable period of time as well as for the categories fans, subscribers, persons reached and interacting persons, the following data is provided to us by Facebook in relation to our Facebook page:  
Total number of page views, "like" information, page activities, post interactions, reach, video views, post reach, comments, shared content, responses, proportion of men and women, country and city origin, language, views and clicks in the shop, clicks on route planners, clicks on phone numbers. It also provides information about the Facebook groups linked to our Facebook page. Due to the constant development of Facebook, the availability and processing of data is changing, so we refer to the Facebook Privacy Policy (<https://www.facebook.com/policy.php>) for further details. We use this aggregate data to make our contributions and activities on our Facebook page more attractive to users. To this end, we have agreed with Facebook on the so-called "Page Insights Supplement" regarding the person responsible ("Page Insights Supplement").

We process your personal data on the basis of our legitimate interest in communication with you. Furthermore, you may be asked by the provider of the respective social medium for consent to the processing of your data.

We have no influence on the data and data processing processes collected by the provider of the respective medium, nor are we aware of the full extent of data collection, the purposes of processing, the storage periods. We also have no information on the deletion of the data collected by the respective provider. Accordingly, we would like to point out that the assertion of rights of persons concerned must be made against the provider, since only the provider ultimately has direct access to the data collected and can take appropriate measures and provide information. We must therefore forward enquiries addressed to us to the provider.

In case of further Information is needed with regard to the data processing processes, , please contact the provider directly: 

### Sending of newsletters

We offer you the option of subscribing to our newsletters on our website and via embedded frames on our social media platforms. If you have given your consent to receiving the respective newsletter, we use your e-mail address and, where applicable, your name to send (customised where possible) information about the RWE Group. We store and process these data for the purpose of sending the newsletter.

Newsletters contain information about the RWE Group. The current newsletters are especially as follows:

  * Investor Relations newsletter
  * RWE AG newsletter
  * Job Alert newsletter

The legal basis for the aforementioned data processing is your consent in accordance with Article 6 Para 1 lit. a) of the GDPR.

We use the double opt-in procedure to ensure that no errors are made when the e-mail address is entered. Once you have entered your e-mail address in the registration field we will send you a confirmation link. Your e-mail address will only be saved in our mailing list after you have clicked on this confirmation link.

You can revoke your consent to receiving the relevant newsletter with future effect at any time, e.g. by unsubscribing from the newsletter on our website. You can find the link to the unsubscription page at the end of each newsletter. The lawfulness of the processing of your personal data remains unaffected by revocation up until the time of revocation. Your personal data will be deleted 6 months after the unsubscription is received.

If external processors are appointed to send the newsletter, they shall be bound by contract in accordance with Article 28 of the GDPR.

### Questions and Annotations

As a user of our website you have the right to receive information about your saved personal data and the reason of the data process in case any personal data is collected through the website. In case of personal data collection you can have your collected personal data corrected, blocked or deleted. For these purposes or if you have any questions or comments concerning the data privacy of RWE you are welcome to contact us under [datenschutz@rwe.com](mailto:datenschutz@rwe.com).

You have the right to object at any time to the processing of your data on the basis of a balancing of interests or in the public interest if there are reasons for doing so which arise from your particular situation. This also applies to profiling based on this provision.

If you file an objection, we will no longer process your personal data unless we can prove imperative grounds for processing worthy of protection which outweigh your interests, rights and freedoms, or the processing serves the assertion, exercise or defence of legal claims.

The objection can be made without form and should be addressed as far as possible to:

RWE AG, Altenessener Str. 35, 45128 Essen, E-Mail [ds-koordination.rwe@rwe.com](mailto:ds-koordination.rwe@rwe.com)

Furthermore, you have the right to complain to a supervisory authority. You are free to contact the competent supervisory authority of the State Commissioner for Data Protection and Freedom of Information North Rhine-Westphalia (Postfach 20 04 44 in 40102 Düsseldorf) on data protection issues.

The further development of the Internet also affects our data protection strategy. Changes will be announced in good time on this page.

RWE Group 2018, Essen

* * *

* * *
